Mss.B.M381 Mss.B.M381
American Philosophical Society
Correspondence and accounts of the Mason and Dixon survey, 1758-1769
Mss.B.M381
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
Correspondence from Charles Mason and Jeremiah Dixon to Thomas Birch, and Nevil Maskelyne to Charles Mason, relating to the survey, and the transits of Venus (1761,1769).
21 photocopies; 1 microfilm reel
Dixon, Jeremiah
Mason, Charles, 1728-1786
Box 1
Reel 1
Related Archival Materials note
See also: Minutes and papers of the Mason and Dixon survey, 1760-1768 (Mss.974.8.P383).
Early American History Note
The Mason and Dixon Survey Collection at the APS consists of 1.) two volumes relating to their work drawing a border between Pennsylvania and Maryland and 2.) a box of correspondence. The portion of the collection being described here consists of the correspondence. This part of the collection is a box of photostats, mostly from 1761 and 1769, that include field reports and other correspondence.
The other portion of the Mason and Dixon Collection (Mss.974.8.P383) contains two volumes. One details the Penn family’s costs, which goes into specific details about items purchased and used for the venture. The second volume is a manuscript copy of the commissioners’ minutes from 1760-1768. The commissioners, who were representatives of both Baltimore and Penn, gave directions to Mason and Dixon. The minutes contain negotiations between the commissioners, which provide insight into surveying methods and the various disagreements between the two sides about boundaries, particularly as they relate to the Delmarva Peninsula. There are a few mentions of Indians and diplomacy, especially around 1767 when Mason and Dixon were extending the line into the Ohio Country.
Biographical/Historical note
Charles Mason (Oakridge Lynch, Gloucestershire, April 1728– Philadelphia, October 25, 1786) was an English astronomer who made significant contributions to 18th-century science and American history, particularly through his involvement with the survey of the Mason-Dixon line, which came to mark the division between the northern and southern United States (1764-1768).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired, 1947; provenance unknown.
Existence and Location of Originals note
Originals in British Museum, Historical Society of Pennsylvania, Maryland Historical Society, and Royal Society.
Birch, Thomas; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811; Colonial Politics; General Correspondence; Government Affairs; Maps and Surveys; Maryland -- Boundaries.; Mason-Dixon Line.; Meteorology.; Official Government Documents and Records; Pennsylvania -- Boundaries.; Pennsylvania History; Science and Technology; Surveying and Maps; Surveys.; Transits.; Venus (Planet)
- 21 items photostats and typescripts. 1758-1771
  - Memoranda to Revd. Dr. [James] Bradley, May 1, 1758; 8" x 13"; Mason, Charles, 1728-1786
    Scope and Contents note
    Greenwich, Typescript of D. 1p. Memo. relative to alternations made on astronomical instruments, July 5,1742-July 1753. From original in Bodleian library.
  - Letter to [Thomas Birch], Oct. 2, 1760; Dixon, Jeremiah
    Cockfield, Photostat of A.L.S. 1p. From original in British Museum.
  - Letter to Tho[ma]s Birch, Nov. 24, 1760; Mason, Charles, 1728-1786
    Portsmouth, Photostat of L.S: C. Mason, J. Dixon. 1p. and add. Scientific instruments. From original in British museum.
  - Letter to Charles Mason, Nov. 29, 1760; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
    London, Photostate of A.L.S. 4p.,add. Instructions for observing the Transit of Venus. From original in Maskelyne Collection. Greenwich observatory.
  - Letter to Tho[ma]s Birch, Dec. 1, 1760; Dixon, Jeremiah
    Portsmouth Point, Photostat of A.L.S. 1p. and add. Everything in readiness for sailing except orders from the directors of the India co. From original in British Museum.
  - Letter to Tho[ma]s Birch, Dec. 8, 1760; Dixon, Jeremiah
    Portsmouth, Photostat of A.L.S. 1p. and add. Capt. Smith's sailing instructions. From original in British Museum.
  - Mason and Dixon's expences &c. to the accompt of the Royal society, Oct. 23, Oct. 5, 1760, 1761; Mason, Charles, 1728-1786
    Photostat of D. 2p. From original in Maskelyne Collection, Greenwich observatory. Contains also: Receipt from Charles Mason to Nevil Maskelyne; Jan. 2, 1762.
  - Letter to Tho[ma]s Birch, Jan. 12, 1761; Dixon, Jeremiah
    Plymouth, Photostat of A.L.S. 1p. and add. Report to the Royal Society on the condition of his vessel after an encounter with a French ship; impossible to now reach Indian in time for the observations. From original in British Museum.
  - Letter to [Thomas] Birch, Feb. 27, 1761; Dixon, Jeremiah
    St. Cruz in the Island Tenarif, Photostat of A.L.S. 1p. and add. Report to the Royal Society on the voyage thus far. From original in British Museum.
  - Letter to Tho[ma]s Birch, May 6, 1761; Dixon, Jeremiah
    Cape of Good Hope, Photostat of A.L.S. 1p. and add. Making all possible dispatch to erect an observatory in time for the Transit. From original in British Museum.
  - Receipt for ten pounds from Nevil Maskelyne, Jan. 2, 1762; Mason, Charles, 1728-1786
    St. Helena, Photostat of A.D. (On same sheet with Mason and Dixon's expences...Oct. 23,1760-Oct. 5, 1761) From original in Maskelyne Collection, Greenwich observatory.
  - Letter to Charles Mason, Jan. 31, 1769; 8 1/2" x 11"; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
    Greenwich, Typescript of L. 2p. Terms settled for Mason's visit to Ireland to observe the transit of Venus. From original in Maskelyne Collection, Greenwich observatory.
  - Letter to Cha[rle]s Mason, Feb. 7, 1769; 8 1/2" x 11"; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
    Greenwich, Typescript of L. 1p. Astronomical instruments. From original in Maskelyne Collection, Greenwich observatory.
  - Letter to Charles Mason, May 8, 1769; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
    Greenwich, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and add. Astronomical observations and instruments. From original in Maskelyne Collection, Greenwich observatory.
  - Letter to Charles Mason, May 23, 1769; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
    Greenwich, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and add. Astronomical observations; Transit of Venus. From original in Maskelyne Collection, Greenwich observatory.
  - Letter to Charles Mason, June 24, 1769; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
  - Letter to Charles Mason, Aug. 7, 1769; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
    Greenwich, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and add. Astronomical observations; Transit of Venus; mentions Dr. Smith of Pennsylvania. From original in Maskelyne Collection, Greenwich observatory.
  - Letter to Charles Mason, Sept. 7, 1769; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
    Greenwich, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and add. Astronomical observations. From original in Maskelyne Collection, Greenwich observatory.
  - Letter to Charles Mason, Oct. 6, 1769; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
    Greenwich, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and add. Astronomical observations. Mr. Winthrop and Transit of Venus. From original in Maskelyne Collection, Greenwich obervatory.
  - Letter to Charles Mason, Nov. 9, 1769; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
    London, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p. and add. Observations of the Transit of Vernus made by various persons including [John] Winthrop. From original in Maskelyne Collection, Greewich observatory.
  - Letter to Nevil Maskelyne, Jan. 30, 1771; 8 1/2" x 11"; Mason, Charles, 1728-1786
    Tetbury, Typescript of L. 1p. Astronomical affairs. From original in Maskelyne Collection, Greenwich observatory.
  - Letter to Charles Mason, Undated; 8 1/2" x 11"; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
    Greenwich; Tuesday morn. Typescript of L. 1p. Transit of Venus of June 6, 1761. From original in Maskelyne Collection, Greenwich Observatory.
- Journal (copy), 1763-1768, B M381.1; 1.0 Reel(s); 1 microfilm copy (from microfilm) of original in the National Archives.; Journal during the survey of the Pennsylvania-Maryland line, 1763-1768. (Reel 1)
  Existence and Location of Originals note
  Originals in the National Archives.